Today we're going to not talk about sorting.
今天我们不再讨论排序
This is an exciting new development.
这是个令人兴奋的进步
We're going to talk about another problem,
我们要讨论另外一个问题
a related problem, but a different problem.
一个和排序有关但是又不同的问题
which we would like to solve in linear time.
也用线性时间解决
Last class we talked about
上节课我们讨论到
we could do sorting in linear time.
我们可以用线性时间排序
To do that we needed some additional assumptions.
只是我们需要一些额外的假设
Today we're going to look at a problem
今天我们要看这样一个问题
that really only needs linear time, even though at
这个问题只需要线性时间
first glance it might look like it requires sorting.
即使刚看上去它需要排序
So this is going to be an easier problem.
这是一个简单一些的问题
The problem is I give you a bunch of numbers.
问题是这样的  我给你一些数
Let's call them elements.
我们称它们为元素
And they are in some array, let's say.
假设这些元素在一个数组中
And they're in no particular order, so unsorted.
没有一个特别的顺序  即无序
I want to find the kth smallest element.
我想找到第k小的数
This is called the element of rank k.
这个数被称为排名第k的元素
In other words, I have this list of numbers which is unsorted.
换句话说  我有一组无序的数
And, if I were to sort it,
假如我能够把这些数排序
I would like to know what the kth element is.
我就能知道第k号元素是什么
But I'm not allowed to sort it.
但是现在不允许排序
One solution to this problem, this is the naive algorithm,
解决这个问题的一种原始的方案
is you just sort and then return the kth element.
是排序并返回第k号元素
This is another possible definition of the problem.
这是这个问题的一种解
And we would like to do better than that.
我们希望有更好的方案
So you could sort, what's called the array A,
将数组A排序
and then return A of K.
返回A[k]
That is one thing we could do.
是一种我们可以做的方案
And if we use heap sort or mergesort,
如果我们用堆排序或者归并排序
this will take n lg n time.
会使用nlogn的时间
We would like to do better than n lg n.
我们希望有比nlogn更好的解
Ideally linear time.
最好是线性时间
The problem is pretty natural, straightforward.
这个问题是很自然的
It has various applications.
这个问题有许多应用
Depending on how you choose k, k could be any number
具体是什么取决于你对k的选择
between 1 and n. For example,
k是1到n之间的任意数
if we choose k=1 that element has a name.
如果我们选k等于1
Any suggestions of what the name is?
这个元素有个名字  是什么名字呢
The minimum. That's easy.
最小值  很简单
Any suggestions on how we could find the minimum element
有人说下在线性的时间里
in an array in linear time? Right.
我们怎么找到最小的元素  没错
Just scan through the array.
遍历整个数组
Keep track of what the smallest number is that you've seen.
记录下你见过的最小的数
The same thing with the maximum, k=n.
求最大值也一样  k=n
These are rather trivial.
求这些值相当没意思
But a more interesting version of the order
但是这个问题的一个更有趣的版本
statistic problem is to find the median.
是找出中位数
This is either k equals n plus 1 over 2 floor or ceiling.
(n+1)/2的向上或者向下取整
I will call both of those elements medians.
这两个元素都叫做中位数
Finding the median of an unsorted array in linear time
线性时间内找出无序数列的中位数
is quite tricky.
有点意思
And that sort of is the main goal of this lecture,
这就是这次课的主要目标
to be able to find the medians.
找到中位数
For free we're going to be able
实际上我们任意可以找到
to find the arbitrary kth smallest element,
第k小的元素
but typically we're most interested in finding the median.
但有代表性的  我们希望找到中位数
And on Friday in recitation you'll see why that is so useful.
在周五的习题课上  你会知道这为什么很有用
There are all sorts of situations where you can use median
有很多使用分治策略的情况下
for really effective divide-and-conquer without having to sort.
你都可以用中位数  而且不需要排序
You can solve a lot of problems in linear time as a result.
因此你可以线性解决很多问题
And we're going to cover today two algorithms for finding order statistics.
今天我们要谈顺序统计问题的的两个算法
Both of them are linear time.
这两个算法都是线性时间
The first one is randomized,
第一个算法是随机的
so it's only linear expected time.
所以只是期望时间是线性时间
And the second one is worst-case linear time,
第二个算法考虑最坏情况
and it will build on the randomized version.
以第一个算法为基础
Let's start with a randomize divide-and-conquer algorithm.
我们先讲一个随机的分治算法
This algorithm is called rand-select.
这个算法叫随机选择
And the parameters are a little bit more than what we're used to.
参数与你们平时见的不太一样
The order statistics problem you're given an array A.
这个顺序问题里面  已有数组A
And here I've changed notation
这里我改变记号
and I'm looking for the ith smallest element,
我要找第i小的元素
so *i* is the index I'm looking for.
所以i是我要找的序号
And I'm also going to change the problem a little bit.
我还要再改变下问题
And instead of trying to find it in the whole array,
我不从整个数组里面找第i个数
I'm going to look in a particular interval of the array,
而是从其中一段中来找
A from p up to q.
在A里从p到q找
We're going to need that for a recursion.
我们要用那个函数做递归
This better be a recursive algorithm
用递归算法
because we're using divide-and-conquer.
因为我们要用分治策略
Here is the algorithm.
下面是算法
base case. Pretty simple.
基本情形  这很简单
Then we're going to use part of the quicksort algorithm,
我们要使用一部分快速排序
randomized quicksort.
随机快速排序
We didn't actually define this subroutine two lectures ago,
前两节课我们没有真正定义这个子程序
but you should know what it does,
但你应该知道这个函数做什么了
especially if you've read the textbook.
如果你读了课本的话
This says in the array A pick a random element,
在数组A从p到q之间
so pick a random index between p and q,
在p和q之间随机找个数
swap it with the first element, then call partition.
和第一个元素交换  再调用划分函数
And partition uses that first element to split the rest of the
划分函数用第一个元素将数组划分成两部分
array into less than or equal to that random partition and
一部分都小于等于第一个划分元素
greater than or equal to that partition.
另一部分大于等于划分元素
This is just picking a random partition element between p and q,
在p和q之间随机选择一个划分
cutting the array in half, although the two sizes may not be equal.
将数组分成可能不相等的两部分
And it returns the index of that partition element,
然后返回划分元素的序号
some number between p and q.
是p和q之间的某个数
And we're going to define k to be this particular value, r minus p plus 1.
我们设k为r-p+1
And the reason for that is that k is then the rank of the partition element.
这么做是因为k是划分元素的序号
This is in A[p...q].
它在A[p...q]之中
Let me draw a picture here.
我画个图
We have our array A. It starts at p and ends at q.
数组A从p开始到q结束
There is other stuff, but for this recursive all we
还有其他元素  不过这一步递归我们只考虑
care about is p up to q.
p和q之间的元素
We pick a random partition element, say this one,
我们随机取一个元素  比如这个
and we partition things so that everything in here, let's call this r,
我们把元素从这里划分  假设是r
is less than or equal to A[r]
使得前面的小于或等于A[r]
and everything up here is greater than or equal to A[r].
后面的这些元素都大于等于A[r]
And A[r] is our partition element.
A[r]是划分元素
After this call, that's what the array looks like.
在调用之后  数组就像这样
And we get r. We get the index of where partition element is stored.
r这里是划分元素的位置
The number of elements that are less than or equal to A[r]
小于等于A[r]元素的数目
and including r is r minus p plus 1.
包括r本身  是r-p+1
There will be r minus p elements here,
这里有r-p个元素
and we're adding 1 to get this element.
加上这里的一个
And, if you start counting at 1,
如果从1开始计数
if this is rank 1, rank 2,
如果这是1号  这是2号
this element will have rank k.
那么这个元素会是第k号
That's just from the construction in the partition.
可以从划分的结构上得到这些结果
And now we get to recurse. And there are three cases --
现在我们开始递归  有三种情况
-- depending on how i relates to k.
取决于i和k的关系
Remember i is the rank that we're looking for,
i是我们要找的序号
k is the rank that we happen to get out of this random partition.
k是我们划分元素在划分后的位置
We don't have much control over k,
k的位置是巧合
but if we're lucky i=k.
但如果幸运的话i=k
That's the element we want.
那么就是我们要找的元素
Then we just return the partition element.
我们只需返回划分元素
More likely is that the element we're looking for is either to
更有可能的是  我们寻找的元素
the left or to the right. And if it's to the left we're
在划分元素的左边或者右边
going to recurse in the left-hand portion of the array.
如果在左边的话  我们递归左边这块
And if it's to the right we're going to recurse in the right-hand portion.
在右边的话  我们递归右边的这块
So, pretty straightforward at this point.
这点我们很清楚了
I just have to get all the indices right.
现在写在右边的元素
Either we're going to recurse on the part between p and r minus 1,
我们要么递归p到r-1的这块
that's this case. The rank we're looking for is
这是这种情况
to the left of the rank of element A[r].
我们要找的序号在A[r]左边
Or, we're going to recurse on the right part
或者我们递归右边的这块
between r plus 1 and q.
从r-1到q
Where we recurse on the left part
当我们在左边这块递归时
the rank we're looking for remains the same,
我们需找的序号不发生变化
but when we recurse on the right part the rank we're
但当我们在右边这块递归时
looking for gets offset.
我们需要做些偏移
Because we sort of got rid of the k elements over here.
因为我们要除去这里的k个元素
I should have written this length is k.
这里的长度是k
We've sort of swept away k ranks of elements.
我们去掉左边的k个元素
And now within this array we're
在剩下的数组中
looking for the i minus kth smallest element.
我们寻找第i-k小的元素
That's the recursion. We only recurse once.
这就是递归式  我们只做一个递归
And random partition is not a recursion.
随机划分不是递归
That just takes linear time.
这只需要线性时间
And the total amount of work we're doing here
我们总共做的工作量应该是
should be linear time plus one recursion.
线性的时间加上一次递归
And we'd next like to see
下面我们要看下
what the total running time is in expectation,
预期的运行时间是多少
but let's first do a little example --
不过我们首先做个例子
-- to make this algorithm perfectly clear.
好让你们弄清楚这个算法
Let's suppose we're looking for the seventh smallest element in this array.
假设在数组中找第7小的元素
And let's suppose, just for example,
举个例子
that the pivot we're using is just the first element.
假设我们把第一个元素做为划分元素
So, nothing fancy.
这是为了简单起见
I would have to flip a few coins in order to
如果要随机找个元素我得抛几次硬币
generate a random one, so let's just pick this one.
所以我们就选第一个元素
If I partition at the element 6,
如果我以6作为划分元素
this is actually an example we did two weeks ago,
这就是我们两周前讨论的例子
and I won't go through it again,
我就不讨论了
but we get the same array, as we did two weeks ago,
我们得到和两周前一样的数组
namely 2 5 3 6 8 13 10 and 11.
就是2 5 3 6 8 13 10和11
If you run through the partitioning algorithm,
运行划分算法
that happens to be the order that it throws the elements into.
元素就会如此排列
And this is our position r. This is p here.
这里是r  这里是p
It's just 1. And q is just the end.
p为1  q是结尾
And I am looking for the seventh smallest element.
我要找的是第7小的数
And it happens when I run this partition
进行划分后
that 6 falls into the fourth place.
数字6落在了第4的位置
And we know that means, because all the elements here
因为左边的小于6
are less than 6 and all the elements here are greater than 6,
并且右边的大于6
if this array were sorted, 6 would be right here in position four.
排序后  数字6还是会在第4这个位置
So, r here is 4.
所以r是4
Yeah? The 12 turned into an 11?
有问题吗  12变成11了
This was an 11, believe it or not.
这是11  不管你信不信
Let me be simple. Sorry.
写清楚点  不好意思
Sometimes my ones look like twos.
有时我写的1有点像2
Not a good feature. That's an easy way to cover.
这点不好  不过很好改正
Don't try that on exams.
考试的时候可别这样
Oh, that one was just a two. No.
我那个1其实是2  不行
Even though we're not sorting the array,
虽然我们没排序
we're only spending linear work here to partition by 6.
只是用线性的时间按6划分
We know that if we had sorted the array 6 would fall here.
我们也知道  如果排序6还是在这里
We don't know about these other elements.
其他的原始在哪不知道
They're not in sorted order, but from the properties of
它们不是顺序的  但是根据划分的性质
partition we know 6 went the right spot.
6是在正确的位置
We now know rank of 6 is 4. We happened to be looking for 7
6是第4小的  我们要找的是第7小
and we happened to get this number 4.
根据这是第4小的
We want something over here.
结果在这边
It turns out we're looking for 10, I guess. No, 11.
答案是10  我猜  不  是11
There should be eight elements in this array,
总共有8个元素
so it's the next to max.
所以是第二大
Max here is 13, I'm cheating here.
最大值是13  我在作弊
The answer we're looking for is 11.
答案是11
We know that what we're looking for is in the right-hand part
我们知道答案在右半边
because the rank we're looking for is 7, which is bigger than 4.
因为要找第7小  而7大于4
Now, what rank are we looking for in here?
在这部分中是第几小
Well, we've gotten rid of four elements over here.
去掉前面的4个数字
It happened here that k is also 4 because p is 1 in this example.
因为p是1  所以k是4
The rank of 6 was 4.
6是第4小的数
We throw away those four elements. Now we're looking for
去掉前4个数  结果是
rank 7 minus 4 which is 3.
7减4等于3
And, indeed, the rank 3 element here is still 11.
确实是  第3小的数是11
So, you recursively find that. That's your answer.
递归的查找  这就是答案
Now that algorithm should be pretty clear.
现在算法很清晰了吧
The tricky part is to analyze it.
困难的地方是分析它
And the analysis here is quite a bit like randomized quicksort,
这里的分析和随机化快速排序类似
although not quite as hairy,
尽管没那么复杂
so it will go faster.
所以能讲快点
But it will be also sort of a nice review
但是这也是对随机化快速排序分析
of the randomized quicksort analysis which was a bit
的一次复习  有点复杂
tricky and always good to see a couple of times.
多练两次也有好处
We're going to follow the same kind of outline as before to
在分析此算法的期望运行时间前
look at the expected running time of this algorithm.
我们照例进行一些概述
And to start out we're going to, as before,
就像往常  在开始前
look at some intuition just to feel good about ourselves.
我们通过直觉来自我感觉良好
Also feel bad as you'll see.
或者糟糕  马上你就看到了
Let's think about two sort of extreme cases,
思考一下两个极端的例子
a good case and the worst case.
好的情况和最坏情况
And I should mention that in all of the analyses today
我提前说一点  今天所有的分析的前提是
we assume the elements are distinct.
假设元素不相等
It gets really messy if the elements are not distinct.
如果有相等元素  就很乱
And you may even have to change the algorithms a little bit
甚至得修改一下算法
because if all the elements are equal,
因为如果所有元素都相等
if you pick a random element,
选择一个随机元素
the partition does not do so well.
划分效果就很差
But let's assume they're all distinct,
我们假设全部都不相等
which is the really interesting case.
这才是真正有意思的情况
A pretty luck case --
一个很幸运的情况
I mean the best cases we partition right in the middle.
最好情况就是在正中划分
The number of elements to the left of our partition is equal
划分在左边的元素的数量等于
to the number of elements to the right of our partition.
在右边的元素数
But almost as good would be some kind of 1/10 to 9/10 split.
但是1/10到1/9的划分也几乎一样好
Any constant fraction, we should feel that.
任何的常数比例的划分  这样说
Any constant fraction is as good as 1/2.
都和1/2的划分一样好
Then the recurrence we get is,
得到的递归式是
let's say at most, this bad. So, it depends.
最坏的情况  这得看情况
If we have let's say 1/10 on the left and 9/10 on the right
假设1/10在左边  9/10在右边
every time we do a partition.
每次划分
It depends where our answer is.
情况都不同
It could be if I is really small it's in the 1/10 part.
如果找的数很小  则在1/10中
If I is really big it's going to be in the 9/10 part,
如果大  则在9/10中
or most of the time it's going to be in the 9/10 part.
大多数时候  它会在9/10中
We're doing worst-case analysis within the lucky case,
在幸运的情况中作最坏情况分析
so we're happy to have upper bounds.
我们更乐意得到上界
I will say T(n) is at most t of T(9/10n)+Theta(n).
T(n)最大是T(9/10n)+Θ(n)
Clearly it's worse if we're in the bigger part.
显然在更大的这部分  情况更坏
What is the solution to this recurrence?
怎么求解这个递归式
Oh, solving recurrence was so long ago.
解递归式是很早以前的事了
What method should we use for solving this recurrence?
应该用哪种方法
The master method. What case are we in?
主方法  这是哪一种情况
Three. Good.
第三种  正确
You still remember. This is Case 3.
你还记得呀  就是第三种
We're looking at n^(logba). b here is 10/9,
n^(logba)  b是10/9
although it doesn't really matter because a is 1.
这并不重要  因为a是1
log base anything of 1 is 0. So, this is n^0 which is 1.
任意底数的log1都是0  n⁰等于1
And n is polynomially larger than 1.
n多项式地大于1
This is going to be O(n), which is good.
结果就是Θ(n)  很好
That is what we want, linear time.
就是我们想要的  线性时间复杂度
If we're in the lucky case, great.
如果够幸运的话  效果很好
Unfortunately this is only intuition.
不幸的是  这只是直觉
And we're not always going to get the lucky case.
我们并不是每次都是幸运的
We could do the same kind of analysis as we did
我们可以做和随机化快速排序相同
with randomized quicksort.
的那些分析
If you alternate between lucky and unlucky,
如果交替幸运和不幸运
things will still be good, but let's just talk about the unlucky case
结果还是好的  再说说不幸运的情况
to show how bad things can get.
看看能有多糟
And this really would be a worst-case analysis.
这是真正的最坏情况分析
The unlucky case we get a split of 0:n-1.
我们得到了一个0和n-1的划分
Because we're removing the partition element either way.
因为无论如何我们都去掉了划分元素
And there could be nothing less than the partition element.
没有比划分元素更小的了
We have 0 on the left-hand side
左边没有任何元素
and we have n-1 on the right-hand side.
右边有n-1个元素
Now we get a recurrence like T(n)=T(n-1) plus linear cost.
现在的递归式是T(n)=T(n-1)+Θ(n)
And what's the solution to that recurrence? N^2.
结果是多少  n²
Yes. This one you should just know.
对  这个你们应该知道
It's n^2 because it's an arithmetic series.
因为是等差级数  所以是n²
And that's pretty bad.
这相当糟糕
This is much, much worse than sorting
比起先排序再选择第i小的元素
and then picking the ith element.
还差的很远
In the worst-case this algorithm really sucks,
最坏情况  这个算法效率巨差
but most of the time it's going to do really well.
但是大多数时候  它都很好
And, unless you're really, really unlucky and every coin
除非你背到家了
you flip gives the wrong answer, you won't get this case
每次掷硬币都输  不然不会如此
and you will get something more like the lucky case.
你一般会得到一个幸运的情况
At least that's what we'd like to prove.
至少我们马上就要证明它
And we will prove that the expected running time here is linear.
我们要证明期望运行时间是线性的
So, it's very rare to get anything quadratic.
出现二次方复杂度的情况极少
But later on we will see how to make the worst-case linear as well.
等会儿会将最坏情况也变成线性复杂度
This would really, really solve the problem.
这才真正解决了问题
Let's get into the analysis.
现在来分析
Now, you've seen an analysis much like this before.
你们之前见过一个类似的分析
What do you suggest we do
说说该怎么办
in order to analyze this expected time?
为了分析期望运行时间
It's a divide-and-conquer algorithm,
这是一个分治算法
so we kind of like to write down the recurrence on something
所以我们希望写出关于运行时间
resembling the running time.
的递归式
I don't need the answer, but what's the first step that we might do
我不要答案  告诉我分析这个算法
to analyze the expected running time of this algorithm?
期望时间的第一步是什么
Sorry?
能再说一遍吗
Look at different cases, yeah. Exactly.
看看有哪些不同的情况  完全正确
We have all these possible ways
我们有多种的
that random partition could split.
划分可能
It could split 0 to the n-1. It could split in half.
可能分为0和n-1  也可能对半分
There are n choices where it could split.
一共有n种划分可能
How can we break into those cases?
如何才能分析这么多的情况
Indicator random variables. Cool.
指示器随机变量  正确
Exactly. That's what we want to do.
就是要这样做
Indicator random variable suggests that what we're
指示器随机变量说明
dealing with is not exactly just a function T(n)
我们处理的不只是函数T(n)
but it's a random variable.
而且是一个随机变量
This is one subtlety.
这点很妙
T(n) depends on the random choices,
T(n)依赖随机选择
so it's really a random variable.
所以它是一个随机变量
And then we're going to use indicator random variables
接着我们要使用指示器随机变量
to get a recurrence on T(n).
为的是写出T(n)的递归式
So, T(n) is the running time of rand-select on an input of size n.
T(n)是算法在规模为n下的运行时间
And I am also going to write down explicitly an assumption
我还要明确的写出
about the random numbers.
关于随机数的假设
That they should be chosen independently from each other.
那就是它们的选择是相互独立的
Every time I call random partition,
每次调用随机划分时
it's generating a completely independent random number
得到的结果完全独立于
from all the other times I call random partition.
其它时候的调用
That is important, of course, for this analysis to work.
要分析是正确的  这点很重要
We will see why some point down the line.
接下来就能看到为什么
And now, to sort of write down an equation for T(n)
现在  为了写出T(n)的等式
we're going to define indicator random variables, as you suggested.
需要定义指示器随机变量
And we will call it X_k.
我们称它为Xk
And this is for all k=0...n-1.
k等于0到n-1
Indicator random variables either 1 or 0.
指示器随机变量非1即0
And it's going to be 1 if the partition
它是1  当划分是
comes out k on the left-hand side.
分割后左边的数组长度为k
So say the partition generates an k to n-k-1 split
也就是说数组被分割成k和n-k-1两段
and it is 0 otherwise.
否则  Xk的值为0
We have n of these indicator random variables between 0...n-1.
所以给定下标从0到n-1的n个值
And in each case, no matter how the random choice comes out,
不管随机选择怎么实现
exactly one of them will be 1.
每种分割对应的Xk值要么为1
All the others will be 0.
要么为0
Now we can divide out the running time of this algorithm
现在我们根据不同情况
based on which case we're in.
分别分析算法的运行时间
That will sort of unify this intuition that we did
也就是统一分析算法各个步骤
and get all the cases.
得到所有可能的情况
And then we can look at the expectation.
然后我们就能知道期望时间要怎么算
T(n), if we just split out by cases,
如果穷举所有随机分割的情况
we have an upper bound like this.
T(n)的上界是这样得到的
If we have 0 to n-1 split,
如果数组被分割成0和n-1两组
the worst is we have n-1.
最坏情况是递归处理n-1这组
Then we have to recurse in a problem of size n-1.
那么问题就变成在n-1的数组上递归
In fact, it would be pretty hard to recurse in a problem of size 0.
而长度为0的数组可以直接得到结果
If we have a 1 to n-2 split
如果数组被分割为1和n-2两组
then we take the max of the two sides.
期望时间就是左右两个时间中较大的那个
That's certainly going to give us an upper bound
那就肯定能据此找到一个上界
and so on.
以此类推
And at the bottom you get an n-1 to 0 split.
最终数组分割为n-1和0的两组
This is now sort of conditioning on various events,
现在我们就得到了不同分割对应的情况
but we have indicator random variables
但是我们有指示器随机变量Xk
to tell us when these events happen.
来标记每种情况什么时候会发生
We can just multiply each of these values
我们只需要把每种情况下计算得到的值
by the indicator random variable
乘以指示器随机变量Xk
and it will come out 0 if that's not the case
不对应当前分割的情况时Xk值为0
and will come out 1 and give us this value if that happens to be the split.
而对应当前分割的情况时Xk为1
So, if we add up all of those we'll get the same thing.
如果把所有加起来也是一样的
This is equal to the sum over all k
这就等于对k求和
of the indicator random variable times
用指示器随机变量
the cost in that case, which is t of max k,
乘以相应时间代价  T括号内k和n-k-1
and the other side, which is n-k-1,
两种情况下较大的那个值
plus theta n.
再加Θ(n)
This is our recurrence, in some sense,
某种程度上这是对代表运行时间的
for the random variable representing running time.
随机变量T(n)的递归
Now, the value will depend on which case we come into.
现在结果就取决于当前是哪种分割情况
We know the probability of each of these events happening is the same
我们知道每种情况发生的概率是相同的
because we're choosing the partition element uniformly at random,
因为分割基准元素是随机选择的
but we cannot really simplify much beyond this
递归的存在使得要得到期望
until we take expectations.
还要进一步分析
We know this random variable could be as big as n^2.
随机变量的取值可以很大比如为n²
Hopefully it's usually linear.
幸运时则是线性的
We will take expectations of both sides and get what we want.
必须充分考虑以得到我们想要的结果
Let's look at the expectation of this random variable,
让我们来看看随机变量T(n)的期望值
which is just the expectation, I will copy over,
也就是刚才的求和计算式的期望值
summation we have here so I can work on this board.
把它抄写过来这样就可以在这块板上写
I want to compute the expectation of this summation.
我要计算这个求和式的期望值
What property of expectation should I use?
有哪些与期望相关的的属性可以用呢
Linearity, good.
线性很好
We can bring the summation outside.
我们可以把求和计算提到外面来
Now I have a sum of expectation.
现在就变成求一组期望的总和
Let's look at each expectation individually.
让我们分别来看一下每一项期望怎么求
It's a product of two random variables, if you will.
每一项期望都和对应的两个随机变量有关
This is an indicator random variable
也就是这个指示器随机变量
and this is some more complicated function,
还有这个更加复杂的函数
some more complicated random variable
也就是代表运行时间的
representing some running time,
这个更复杂的随机变量
which depends on what random choices are made in that recursive call.
它们的值依赖于递归过程的每次随机选择
Now what should I do?
现在我要怎么做呢
I have the expectation of the product of two random variables.
我要计算两个随机变量之积的期望
Independence, exactly.
准确地说  它们相互独立
If I know that these two random variables are independent
这两个随机变量相互独立的话
then I know that the expectation of the product
那么它们之积的期望
is the product of the expectations.
就等于它们期望之积
Now we have to check are they independent?
现在我们需要验证它们相互独立
I hope so because otherwise there isn't much else I can do.
我希望如此  否则就没有什么能做的了
Why are they independent?
为什么它俩相互独立呢
Sorry? Because we stated that they are, right.
什么  因为我们声明如此
Because of this assumption.
因为这里声明的算法前提
We assume that all the random numbers are chosen independently.
我们声明选择的随机数字都是相互独立的
We need to sort of interpolate that here.
这里需一点补充说明
These X_k's, all the X_k's,
所有这些Xk的值
X_0 up to X_n-1,
从X0到Xn-1
so all the ones appearing in this summation are dependent upon
求和计算式的所有这些Xk值都取决于
a single random choice of this particular call to random partition.
首次划分时产生的随机数
All of these are correlated,
而这些Xk值之间是相关的
because if one of them is 1, all the others are forced to be 0.
因为当其中一个值为1时其余都必须为0
So, there is a lot of correlation among the X_k's.
所以这些Xk值之间是相关的
But with respect to everything that is in here,
但考虑这边的这个式子中
and the only random part is this T(max(kn-k-1)).
T(max(k,n-k-1))是唯一随机的部分
That's a recursive call
那是递归调用求解的
It's making its own choices, its own random numbers
每次递归产生一个随机数
So, any random numbers it chooses here are independent
按照声明每次产生的随机数
with that assumed from the top level recursive call
都会独立于首次调用时产生的随机数
where we chose this number between 0 and n-1
调用时随机数取值范围在0到n-1之间
So, that is the reason that this
这就是该随机变量与这些
random variable is independent from these.
相互独立的原因
The same thing as quicksort, but I know some people got
快速排序也是这样  但是我知道会有人
confused about it a couple lectures ago so I am reiterating.
对前面的内容有些疑惑  所以我重申一次
So, we get the product of expectations,
所以我们得到两个期望值的乘积
E[X_k] times E[T(max(k n-k-1))].
E[Xk]乘以E[T(max(k,n-k-1))]
I mean the order n comes outside,
Θ(n)本来可以放在外面的
but let's leave it inside for now.
现在我们还是把它留在里面
There is no expectation to compute there
Θ(n)的期望不用求
for order n. Order n is order n.
Θ(n)的期望为Θ(n)
What is the expectation of X_k? 1/n,
Xk的期望是多少  1/n
because they're all chosen with equal probability.
因为每一个值都是以相同的概率出现
There is n of them, so the expectation is 1/n.
有n个这样的值所以期望为1/n
The value is either 1 or 0.
值为1或0
We start to be able to split this up.
那么我们就可以将其分开计算
We have 1/n times this expected value of some recursive T call,
我们有1/n乘以函数T的期望
and then we have plus 1 over n times order n,
再加上1/n乘以Θ(n)
also known as a constant, but everything is summed up n times
后面会是常数  但又累加n次
so let's expand this.
我们将其展开
I have the sum k=0 to n-1.
要从k=0加到k=n-1
I guess the 1/n can come outside.
我想这个1/n可以提到外面来
And we have expectation of [T(max(kn-k-1))].
那么就变成求T(max(k,n-k-1))的期望
Lots of snifty braces there.
这里有很多麻烦的括号
And then plus we have, on the other hand, the sum k=0 to n-1.
还要加一个从k=0到k=n-1的求和
Let me just write that out again.
让我来把这个求和式写出来
We have a 1/n in front and we have a Theta(n) inside.
1/n在前面Θ(n)在里面
This summation is n^2.
这个求和式结果为n²
And then we're dividing by n, so this whole thing is, again, order n.
然后还要除以n所以这整个就等于Θ(n)
Nothing fancy happened there.
看起来没什么复杂的
This is really just saying the expectation of order n is order n.
这部分只是说明了Θ(n)的期望就是Θ(n)
Average value of order n is order n.
Θ(n)的平均值就是Θ(n)
What is interesting is this part.
有意思的是这个部分
Now, what could we do with this summation?
现在我们怎么来处理这个求和式呢
Here we start to differ from randomized quicksort
这里不同于随机快速排序
because we have this max.
因为我们要处理函数max
Randomized quicksort we had the sum of T(k) plus T(n-k-1)
随机快速排序要求T(k)加T(n-k-1)的和
because we were making both recursive calls.
因为那时要使函数在两组数据上同时递归
Here we're only making the biggest one.
这里我们只要处理较长的这组数据
That max is really a pain for evaluating this recurrence.
而这里的max确实是一个难处理的部分
How could I get rid of the max? That's one way to think of it.
怎么去掉max呢  想想有什么办法
Exactly. I could only sum up to halfway and then double.
不错  我只要对一半依次求和然后乘2
In other words, terms are getting repeated twice here.
也就是说这里的每个项都出现了两次
When k=0 or when k=n-1, I get the same T(n-1).
k=0时和k=n-1时这里的项都是T(n-1)
When k=1 or n-2, I get the same thing, 2 and n-3.
k=1和k=n-2时  同理2和n-3也一样
What I will actually do is sum from halfway up.
事实上我只要计算这个求和式里一半的项
That's a little bit cleaner.
那样看起来更清楚一点
And let me get the indices right.
让我检查下这个指数对不对
Floor of n/2 up to n-1 will be safe.
n/2向下取整  加到n-1比较可靠
And then I just have E[T(k)],
后面则只要算E(T(k))
except I forgot to multiply by 2,
抱歉  我忘了要乘以2了
so I'm going to change this 1 to a 2.
所以我要把这个1改成2
And order n is preserved.
保留Θ(n)
This is just because each term is appearing twice.
这只是因为每一项都出现了两次
I can factor it out.
提出公因数
And if n is odd, I'm actually double-counting somewhat,
如果n是奇数  实际上重复计算了一个值
but it's certain at most that.
但显然这将不小于原值
So, that's a safe upper bound. And upper bounds are all we
所以上界是可靠的  并且这个上界已满足要求
care about because we're hoping to get linear.
因为我们只希望时间代价是线性的
And the running time of this algorithm is definitely at least linear,
而这个算法的运行时间至少是线性的
so we just need an upper bounded linear.
所以我们只需要一个线性的上界
So, this is a recurrence. E[T(n)] is at most 2/n times the sum
这就是递归  E(T(n))最大为2/n乘以
of half the numbers between 0 and n of E[T(k)]
k从0到n对应的E(T(k))中一半项的和
+Theta(n).
再加Θ(n)
It's a bit of hairy recurrence.
这是一个有点麻烦的递归
We want to solve it, though.
但是我们还是要解决它
And it's actually a little bit easier than the randomized
实际上这会比随机快速排序递归简单一点
quicksort recurrence. We're going to solve it.
我们要解出这个式子
What method should we use? Sorry?
我们应该用什么方法呢  对不起
Master method? Master would be nice,
主定理吗  这个想法不错
except that each of the recursive calls is with a different value of k.
只是这里每次递归调用都对应不同的k值
The master method only works
主定理适用的情况是
when all the calls are with the same value, same size.
每次调用都是相同的参数相同的k值
Alas, it would be nice if we could use the master method.
唉呀  要是这里能用主定理就好了
What else do we have? Substitution.
还有什么别的方法吗  代换法
When it's hard, when in doubt, use substitution.
当遇到很难  解有疑问的情况用代换法
I mean the good thing here is we know what we want.
好的方面是我们知道我们想要做什么
From the intuition at least, which is now erased,
至少从直觉上  这个现在已经擦掉了
we really feel that this should be linear time.
我们确实能猜到结果应该是线性时间
So, we know what we want to prove.
所以我们就知道我们要证明什么
And indeed we can prove it just directly with substitution.
我们确实能直接用代换法证明这个结论
I want to claim there is some constant c greater than zero
我要证明的是存在一个大于0的常数c
such that E[T(n)], according to this recurrence,
根据这个递归过程常数c会使得E(T(n))
is at most c times n. Let's prove that over here.
小于等于c*n  下面是证明过程
As we guessed, the proof is by substitution.
前面已经提到可以用代换法来证明
What that means is we're going to assume, by induction,
用归纳法我们首先假设
that this inequality is true for all smaller n.
对于所有小于n的值都成立
I will just say for less than n. And we need to prove it for n.
假设小于n时成立  然后证明n的情况
We get E[T(n)].
E[T(n)]等于
Now we are just going to expand using the recurrence that we have.
展开这个递归式使用刚才得出的结论
It's at most this. I will copy that over.
不大于这个式子  我们把它抄过来
And then each of these recursive calls
这里每次递归调用
is with some value k that is strictly smaller than n.
一些严格比n小的k值
Sorry, I copied it wrong, floor of n over 2, not zero.
抱歉  我抄错了  是2/n向下取整  不是0
And so I can apply the induction hypothesis to each of these.
按照归纳假设依次代入
This is at most c times k by the induction hypothesis.
根据归纳假设  它≤ck
And so I get this inequality.
于是得到这个不等式
This c can come outside the summation
c可以提到求和号外
because it's just a constant.
因为它是常数
And I will be slightly tedious in writing this down again,
这个写得有点冗长
because what I care about is the summation here that is left over.
因为我要算这个求和
This is a good old-fashioned summation.
这是个经典的求和
And if you remember back to your summation tricks or whatever,
如果你们还记得一点求和技巧的话
you should be able to evaluate this.
就能解出结果来
If we started at zero and went up to n minus 1,
如果从0加到n-1
that's just an arithmetic series,
这是个等差数列
but here we have the tail end of an arithmetic series.
但这里只取原数列的一半求和
And you should know, at least up to theta,
你们应该能算出来
what this is, right?
至少是阶数  它是多少呢
n^2, yeah. It's definitely T(n^2).
二次方  对的  肯定是二次方
But we need here a slightly better upper bond,
但这里我们需要一个更精确的上界
as we will see the constants really matter.
待会我们就会知道该系数的重要性
What we're going to use is that this summation
这个求和式将不大于
is at most 3/8 times n^2. And that will be critical,
3/8*n²  这很关键
the fact that 3/8 is smaller than 1/2, I believe.
3/8比1/2小
So it's going to get rid of this 2.
因此可以消掉这个2
I am not going to prove this. This is an exercise.
后续的证明将作为习题
When you know that it is true, it's easy
证明其实很简单
because you can just prove it by induction.
用归纳法证明就行了
Figuring out that number is a little bit more work,
求得该系数则需要多一些工夫
but not too much more.
但也没多很多
So you should prove that by induction.
你们可以自己用归纳法证明
Now let me simplify.
我化简一下
This is a bit messy, but what I want is c times n.
有点复杂  最终要得到c*n
Let's write it as our desired value minus the residual.
写成c*n减去其余部分的形式
And here we have some crazy fractions.
这里有些复杂的分数
This is 2 times 3 which is 6 over 8
2乘3得6除以8
which is 3/4, right?
就是3/4,  对吧
Here we have 1, so we have to subtract up 1/4 to get 3/4.
这里是1  需要减去1/4得到3/4
And this should be, I guess, 1/4 times c times n.
这里我觉得应该是1/4*c*n
And then we have this theta n
最后还有个1阶余项
with double negation becomes a plus theta n.
负负得正
That should be clear. I am just rewriting that.
刚才重写了一遍  看起来就比较明白了
So we have what we want over here.
我们得到了我们想要的结果
And then we hope that this is nonnegative because what we want
我们希望这个非负
is that this less than or equal to c times n.
然后就得到小于等于c*n
That will be true, provided this thing is nonnegative.
这显然正确  如果这个非负的话
And it looks pretty good
看起来不错
because we're free to choose c however large we want.
因为我们可以取任意大的c
Whatever constant is imbedded in this beta notation is one
无论里面的系数多大都只是个定值
fixed constant, whatever makes this recurrence true.
因此总存在c使递归式成立
We just set c to be bigger than 4 times
当c比4乘该系数大时
that constant and then this will be nonnegative.
那这部分非负
So this is true for c sufficiently large to dwarf that theta constant.
所以不等式在c足够大时成立
It's also the base case.
同样在基本情形也成立
I just have to make the cursory mention that
证明中只用简略地提一句
we choose c large enough so that this claim is true,
当c充分大时条件成立
even in the base case where n is at most some constant.
在基本情形里T(n)为某一常数自然也成立
Here it's like 1 or so
这里约为1
because then we're not making a recursive call.
因为那样我们就不用递归调用了
What we get --
所以我们得到
This algorithm, randomize select,
随机选择算法
has expected running time order n, Theta(n).
运行时间的复杂度期望是Θ(n)
The annoying this is that in the worst-case,
但比较糟糕的是最坏情况
if you're really, really unlucky it's n^2.
最坏情况下的复杂度是Θ(n²)
Any questions before we move on from this point?
还有什么问题吗
This finished off the proof of this fact
这已证明完毕最终得出了
that we have Theta(n) expected time.
期望的时间复杂度是Θ(n)
We already saw the n^2 worst-case.
而最坏情况的复杂度是Θ(n²)
All perfectly clear? Good.
全弄清楚了吗  好的
You should go over these proofs.
你们要好好研究这些证明
They're intrinsically related between
它们阐明了随机快排和随机选择
randomized quicksort and randomized select.
两算法之间的内在联系
Know them in your heart.
要牢记在心
This is a great algorithm that works really well in practice
这个强大的算法在实际工作中很有用
because most of the time you're going to split, say, in the middle,
大部分情况下分割点都会在中间部分
somewhere between a 1/4 and 3/4 and everything is good.
1/4至3/4之间  这很好
It's extremely unlikely that you get the n^2 worst-case.
而出现最坏情况n²的可能性相当小
It would have to happen with like 1 over n^n probability or
可能只有1/nⁿ的概率
something really, really small.
或其他非常非常小的值
But I am a theoretician at least.
但我是理论家
And it would be really nice if you could get Theta(n) in the worst-case.
如果最坏情况的复杂度是Θ(n)就更好了
That would be the cleanest result that
那会是最好的结果
you could hope for because that's optimal.
理想中的最优结果
You cannot do better than Theta(n).
复杂度不可能小于Θ(n)
You've got to look at the elements.
因为你必须把所有数都看一遍
So, you might ask, can we get rid of this worst-case behavior
所以  如何剔除这个最坏情况
and somehow avoid randomization and
并以某种方式避免随机性
guarantee Theta(n) worst-case running time?
保证最坏情况复杂度也是Θ(n)
And you can but it's a rather nontrivial algorithm.
这可以做到  但这是非同一般的算法
And this is going to be one of the most sophisticated that
在我们所见过的算法中
we've seen so far.
最复杂的算法之一
It won't continue to be the most sophisticated algorithm
这并不是最复杂的算法
we will see, but here it is.
但在我们见过的算法中  它是
Worst-case linear time order statistics.
线性的最坏情况时间复杂度
And this is an algorithm by several, all very famous people,
这算法由几个牛人创造
Blum, Floyd,
Blum  Floyd
Pratt, Rivest and Tarjan.
Pratt  Rivest和Tarjan
I think I've only met the B and the R and the T.
我只见过Blum和Rivest和Tarjan
Oh, no, I've met Pratt as well.
哦还见过Pratt
I'm getting close to all the authors.
我倒是跟所有作者都蛮接近的
This is a somewhat old result,
这是个老算法
but at the time it was a major breakthrough
但在当时是个重大突破
and still is an amazing algorithm.
而且现在依然是令人叹服的算法
Ron Rivest is a professor here.
Rivest是MIT的一个教授
You should know him from the R in RSA.
就是RSA公钥体系中的那个R
When I took my PhD comprehensives some time ago,
我当年的博士综合测验的时候
on the cover sheet was a joke question.
封皮是个搞笑的问题
It asked of the authors of
问在这些作者
the worst-case linear time order statistics algorithm,
发明出线性的最坏情况算法的这些人中
which of them is the most rich?
谁最富有
Sadly it was not a graded part of the comprehensive exam,
很遗憾这个不是考试算分的一部分
but it was an amusing question.
但这是个好问题
I won't answer it here because we're on tape,
由于录像的原因我不能告诉你们答案
but think about it.
但想一下这问题
It may not be obvious. Several of them are rich.
这并不显然  好几个人都很富
It's just the question of who is the most rich.
问题是  谁最富
Anyway, before they were rich they came up with this algorithm.
总之  在富起来之前他们创造了这个算法
They've come up with many algorithms since,
他们想出很多算法
even after getting rich, believe it or not.
即使富起来以后  信不信由你
What we want is a good pivot, guaranteed good pivot.
我们需要一个好的主元  保证好的主元
Random pivot is going to be really good.
随机主元看起来是个好方法
And so the simplest algorithm is just pick a random pivot.
最简单的方法正是随机选一个
It's going to be good with high probability.
很大概率上讲都会很好
We want to force a good pivot deterministically.
但我们想选出一个确实很好的主元
And the new idea here is we're going to generate it recursively.
新想法是递归地生成主元
What else could we do but recurse?
除了递归我们还能做什么
Well, you should know from your recurrences that
你们从递归中可以理解
if we did two recursive calls on problems of half the size
如果递归地求解半个问题
and we have a linear extra work
我们需要多做一个线性复杂度的工作
that's the mergesort recurrence,
就像归并排序中的递归
T(n)=2[T(n/2)+Theta(n)].
T(n)=2[T(n/2)+Θ(n)]
You should recite in your sleep.
你们应该做梦都能背出来
That's n lg n.
复杂度是nlogn
So we cannot recurse on two problems of half the size.
我们不能递归地分成两半
We've got to do better.
必须做的更好
Somehow these recursions have to add up to strictly less than n.
所以这个递归的复杂度必须严格小于n
That's the magic of this algorithm.
这算法的神奇之处正是在此
So this will just be called select instead of rand-select.
所以是选择而不是随机选择
And it really depends on an array,
这和初始状态有关
but I will focus on the i-th element that we want to select
但我们只要第i大的元素
and the size of the array that we want to select in.
以及需要查找的数组的大小
And I am going to write this algorithm
我写下这个算法
slightly less formally than randomize-select because
比随机选择稍稍不正式一些
it's a bit higher level of an algorithm.
这个是算法的一点点儿高级抽象
And let me draw over here the picture of the algorithm.
我在这边画一下这个算法
The first step is sort of the weirdest
第一步有些奇怪
and it's one of the key ideas.
这里也是一个算法思想的关键之处
You take your elements,
这些数据
and they are in no particular order,
之间没有什么特殊顺序
so instead of drawing them on a line,
我并不把它们排成一排
I am going to draw them in a 5 by n over 5 grid. Why not?
而是排成5×n/5网格
This, unfortunately, take a little while to draw,
这需要一些时间来画
but it will take you equally long so I will take my time.
你们也需要这么多时间  我就画一下吧
It doesn't really matter what the width is,
宽度无关紧要
but it should be width n over 5
应该是n/5
so make sure you draw your figure accordingly.
你们相应地画五排
Width n over 5, but the height should be exactly 5.
宽度是n/5  高度必须是5
I think I got it right. I can count that high.
我认为我画对了  数一下
Here is 5.
确实是五
And this should be, well,
就应该是五
you know, our number may not be divisible by 5,
有些数不能被5整除
so maybe it ends off in sort of an odd way.
所以最后一列不一样
But what I would like is that these chunks should be floor of n over 5.
这个部分宽度为n/5向下取整
And then we will have, at most, four elements left over.
然后最多剩下4个
So I am going to ignore those. They don't really matter.
忽略这些  它们无关紧要
It's just an additive constant. Here is my array.
只会添加一个常数  这就是我的数组
I just happened to write it in this funny way.
只是画得比较搞怪一些
And I will call these vertical things groups.
每一竖列都是一组
I would circle them, and I did that in my notes,
我可以圈出每一列  像讲义里做的那样
but things get really messy if you start circling.
但是如果画圈  这个图将非常混乱
This diagram is going to get really full, just to warn you.
图会被画得满满的  我只是警告下
By the end it will be almost unintelligible,
到最后将几乎无法辨认
but there it is.
不过...  就是这样
If you are really feeling bored, you can draw this a few times.
如果你觉得无聊  你可以这样画几次
And you should draw how it grows.
你也可以看看会画成什么样
So there are the groups, vertical groups of five.
因此这就是组  每一竖组五个元素
Next step.
下一步
The second step is to recurse.
第二步是递归
This is where things are a bit unusual, well, even more unusual.
这里会有点不一样  甚至很不一样
Oops, sorry. I really should have had a line between one and two
抱歉  我应该在这两步之间空上一行
so I am going to have to move this down
因此我会把第二步移到下面去
and insert it here.
然后把这个加在第一步后面
I ,also in step one, want to find the median of each group.
在第一步中  我们还要找每一组的中值
What I would like to do is just imagine this figure,
想象在这个图中
each of the five elements in each group gets reorganized
每一组中的五个元素重新排列
so that the middle one is the median.
这样中间的那个元素就是中值
So I am going to call these the medians of each group.
这些元素被称为每组的中值
I have five elements so the median is right in the middle.
每一组五个元素  中值就刚好在正中间
There are two elements less than the median,
一组中有两个元素小于中值
two elements greater than the median.
两个元素大于中值
Again, we're assuming all elements are distinct.
同时  假设元素都不相等
So there they are. I compute them.
就是这样  计算它们
How long does that take me?
这要花多长时间
N over five groups, each with five elements,
n/5个组  每一组5个元素
compute the median of each one?
计算每一组的中值
Sorry? Yeah, 2 times n over 5.
什么  对  2*n/5
It's theta n, that's all I need to know.
就是Θ(n)  这就是我想听到的
I mean, you're counting comparisons, which is good.
我的意思是  你考虑了比较  这样很好
It's definitely Theta(n).
这必然是Θ(n)
The point is within each group,
关键是  在每一组中
I only have to do a constant number of comparisons
我只需要做固定次数的比较
because it's a constant number of elements.
因为每一组中元素数目是一定的
It doesn't matter.
这个无所谓
You could use randomize select for all I care.
你可以进行随机选择算法
No matter what you do,
无论你怎么做
it can only take a constant number of comparisons.
它仅仅只需要一定次数的比较
As long as you don't make a comparison more than once.
只要你不重复比较就行
So this is easy.
所以这个很简单
You could sort the five numbers and then look at the third one,
你可以对这五个数进行排序  看第三个数的值
it doesn't matter because there are only five of them.
这个没什么影响  因为只有五个数
That's one nifty idea.
这是一个很好的办法
Already we have some elements
现在已经有一些元素
that are sort of vaguely in the middle but just of the group.
简单的在每一组的中间
And we've only done linear work.
而且只用到线性工作
So doing well so far.
到目前为止还干得不错
Now we get to the second step, which I started to write before,
现在开始第二步  就是我之前开始写的那步
where we recurse.
我们进行递归
So the next idea is, well, we have these floor over n over 5 medians.
下个步骤是...  这层我们有n/5个中值
I am going to compute the median of those medians.
我将要计算出这些中值的中值
I am imagining that I rearranged these.
想象一下我重新排列了这些数
And, unfortunately, it's an even number,
不幸的是这有偶数个数
there are six of them, but I will rearrange so that this guy,
这有6个数但我要进行重组
I have drawn in a second box,
因此这个我画了两个框的数
is the median of these elements
是这些元素的中值
so that these two elements are strictly less than this guy,
因此有2个元素完全小于这个值
these three elements are strictly greater than this guy.
有三个数绝对大于这个值
Now, that doesn't directly tell me anything,
它不会直接告诉我们任何情况
it would seem, it doesn't directly tell me about any of the elements out here.
这看起来没直接告诉我们什么其他信息
We will come back to that.
我们稍后会回来
In fact, it does tell us about some of the elements.
实际上  它确实告诉我们了一些元素信息
But right now this element is just the median of these guys.
不过现在  这个元素只是这些数的中值
Each of these guys is a median of five elements.
而这每个数也只是这五个元素的中值
That's all we know.
这是我们所知道的
If we do that recursively,
如果我们用递归去运算
this is going to take T of n over 5 time.
这个需要花T(n/5)的时间
So far so good.
到目前为止非常的好
We can afford a recursion on a problem of size n over 5 and linear work.
可以用线性的递归法去解决这个n/5大小的问题
We know that works out to linear time.
我们知道这个是线性时间
But there is more. We're obviously not done yet.
不过这还有更多的步骤  我们显然还没有做完
The next step is x is our partition element.
下一步是...  x是我们的划分元素
We partition there.
我们在那儿划分
The rest of the algorithm is just like randomized partition,
剩下的算法就像是随机划分
so we're going to define k to be the rank of x.
因此我们要把k定义为x的排序号
And this can be done, I mean it's n minus r plus 1 or whatever,
这个可以推导出是n-1+r或者别的什么形式
but I'm not going to write out how to do that
不过我不准备写怎么去做的
because we're at a higher level here.
因为我们现在处在更高的层次上
But it can be done.
但是确实是可算的
And then we have the three-way branching.
现在我们有三种情况分支
So if I happens to equal k we're happy.
如果结果恰巧等于k那么很开心
The pivot element is the element we're looking for,
因为这个主元正是我们想要的
but more likely i is either less than k or it is bigger than k.
但是  i更有可能大于或者小于k
And then we make the appropriate recursive call,
选择合适递归调用
so here we recursively select the i-th smallest element
我们用递归的选取第i小的元素
-- -- in the lower part of the array.
在数组的小值部分
Left of the partition element.
也就是划分元素的左侧部分
Otherwise, we recursively select the I minus k-th
如果i>k我们用递归的方法在数组的大值区
smallest element in the upper part of the array.
选择第i-k小的值
I am writing this at a high level
这里我写得比较简略
because we've already seen it.
因为这些都是我们之前已经接触过的
All of this is the same as the last couple steps of randomized select.
所有这些都和前面几步的随机选择一样
That is the algorithm.
这就是整个算法
The real question is why does it work?
关键的问题是这个为什么可行
Why is this linear time?
为什么是线性时间的
The first question is what's the recurrence?
第一个问题是这里的递归是什么
We cannot quite write it down yet
我们现在还不能把它写出来
because we don't know how big
因为我们不知道
these recursive subproblems could be.
这里面的子问题有多大
We're going to either recurse in the lower part or the upper part,
我们要递归上半部分或者下半部分
that's just like before.
就像之前一样
If we're unlucky and we have a split *off* like zero to n minus one,
如果很不幸  我们得到像是0:n-1
this is going to be a quadratic time algorithm.
这将会变成n²时间算法
The claim is that this partition element
矛盾就在于这个划分元素要
is guaranteed to be pretty good and good enough.
非常的好  足够的好
The running time of this thing will be T of something times n,
这个算法的运行时间是T(一个数乘以n)
and we don't know what the something is yet.
我们现在还不知道这个数是什么
How big could it be?
这个值能达到多大
Well, I could ask you.
我可以问问你们
But we're sort of indirect here so I will tell you.
但是这里已经有点复杂了  所以我会直接告诉你们
We have already a recursive call of T of n over 5.
我们已经有了一个递归  需要的时间是T(n/5)
It better be that whatever constant,
这里最好有一个任意的常数
so it's going to be something times n,
这样这里就是n乘以一个常数
it better be that that constant is strictly less than 4/5.
如果这个常数可以完全的小于4/5将会更好
If it's equal to 4/5
如果这个数等于4/5
then you're not splitting up the problem enough
你还没有很好的分割这个问题
you'll get an n lg n running time.
你将会得到一个nlogn的运行时间
If it's strictly less than 4/5
如果这个数严格小于4/5
then you're reducing the problem by at least a constant factor.
那么你至少以常数因子让问题减小
In the sense if you add up all the recursive subproblems,
在这种情况下如果你把所有的子问题加在一起
n over 5 and something times n,
n/5以及一个数乘以n
you get something that is a constant strictly less than one times n.
你将会得到一个严格小于1*n的常数
That forces the work to be geometric.
这样保证了这个算法是几何的
If it's geometric you're going to get linear time.
如果它是几何的  你将会得到线性时间算法
So this is intuition but it's the right intuition.
这是一种直觉  但这种直觉是对的
Whenever you're aiming for linear time keep that in mind.
记住无论何时  你的目标都是一个线性时间算法
If you're doing a divide-and-conquer,
如果你用的是分治法
you've got to get the total subproblem size
你将会得到所有子问题的大小
to be some constant less than one times n.
是一个小于1*n的常数
That will work.
这样就可以运行了
OK, so we've got to work out this constant here.
因此我们需要算出这个常数的值
And we're going to use this figure,
同时我们将用到这张图
which so far looks surprisingly uncluttered.
很难得这张图到现在还很整洁
Now we will make it cluttered.
现在我们要把它变得混乱了
What I would like to do is draw an arrow between two vertices,
我要做的是在两个点之间画一个箭头
two points, elements,
或者说是元素  节点
whatever you want to call them.
随便你想怎么称呼它
Let's call them a and b.
那就把它们叫做a和b
And I want to orient the arrow so it points to a larger value,
我想给这个箭头确定方向  使得它指向较大的值
so this means that a is less than b.
那么这就意味着a小于b
This is notation just for the diagram.
这只是对于这个图的记法
And so this element, I am going to write down what I know.
这个元素...  我将写出我所知道的一切
This element is the median of these five elements.
这个元素是这五个元素的中值
I will suppose that it is drawn
我将标箭头表明
so that these elements are larger than the median,
这些元素大于中值
these elements are smaller than the median.
而这些元素小于中间值
Therefore, I have arrows like this.
因此箭头是这样画的
Here is where I wish I had some colored chalk.
要是有一些彩色粉笔就好了
This is just stating this guy is in the middle of those five elements.
也就是说这个值在这五个元素的中间
I know that in every single column.
每一列都是这样
Here is where the diagram starts to get messy.
这个图开始显得有点混乱了
I am not done yet.
我还没有画完
Now, we also know that this element is the median of the medians.
我们也知道这个元素是这些中值中的中值
Of all the squared elements, this guy is the middle.
对于所有框出的元素来说这个值在正中间
And I will draw it so that these are the ones smaller than the median,
我将标箭头标明这些值小于中值
these are the ones larger than the median.
而这些值大于中值
I mean the algorithm cannot do this.
不过算法并不能做这些
It doesn't necessarily know how all this works.
它不需要知道这一切是怎么完成的
I guess it could, but this is just for analysis purposes.
也许它可以  但这些只是为了分析
We know this guy is bigger than that one and bigger than that one.
我们知道它大于这个元素  同时也大于这个元素
We don't directly know about the other elements.
我们没有办法直接得到其他的元素
We just know that that one is bigger than both of those
我们只知道这个元素比那两个都大
and this guy is smaller than these.
而这个元素又小于这三个
Now, that is as messy as the figure will get.
现在这个图乱的不行了
Now, the nice thing about less than is that it's a transitive relation.
对于小于关系比较有利的是这有一个传递关系
If I have a directed path in this graph,
如果这张图上有一个有向路径
I know that this element is strictly less than that element
可以知道这个元素一定小于那个元素
because this is less than that one and this is less than that one.
因为这个小于这个  这个又小于那个
Even though directly I only know within a column
虽然我只知道每一列中的大小关系
and within this middle row, I actually know
和中间这一行的大小关系  但是实际上
that this element -- This is x, by the way.
我可以推知这个元素  用x来表示的话
This element is larger than all of these elements
这个元素比所有这些元素都大
because it's larger than this one and this one
因为它比这个元素和这个元素都大
and each of these is larger than all of those by these arrows.
而根据箭头方向  这两个元素又比这些大
I also know that all of these elements in this rectangle here,
同时我还知道  这一块区域的元素都是...
and you don't have to do this
我不得不把这张图变得更加混乱了
but I will make the background even more cluttered.
你们不必这样做
All of these elements in this rectangle
这个长方形内的所有元素
are greater than or equal to this one
都大于或者等于这个元素
and all of the elements in this rectangle
而这个长方形内的所有元素
are less than or equal to x.
都小于或者等于元素x
Now, how many are there?
那么已知大小关系的元素有多少个呢
Well, this is roughly halfway
这里大概包括了一半的组
along the set of groups and this is 3/5 of these columns.
而这里是一列的3/5
So what we get is that there are at least --
由此可知  至少有
We have n over 5 groups
总共有n/5个组
and we have half of the groups
取其中的一半
that we're looking at here roughly,
从图上我们可以大概看出来
so let's call that floor of n over 2,
对这个值向下取整
and then within each group we have three elements.
每一个组涉及三个元素
So we have at least 3 times floor of floor of n over 5 over 2 n floor
所有至少有n/5向下取整再除以2向下取整再乘以3个元素
elements that are less than or equal to x.
小于等于元素x
And we have the same that are greater than or equal to x.
大于等于元素x的元素个数也是这样
Let me simplify this a little bit more.
现在再来简化一下
I can also give you some more justification,
我还会给出一些证明过程
and we drew the picture, but just for why this is true.
我们画了图  但只是为了证明这是正确的
We have at least n over 5 over 2 group medians
我们有至少这么多个组内中间值
that are less than or equal to x.
它们小于或者等于元素x
This is the argument we use.
这是我们在证明时要用到的条件
We have half of the group medians are less than
这些组内中间值中有一半都小于或等于x
or equal to x because x is the median of the group median,
因为元素x是组内中间值的中间值
so that is no big surprise.
这很容易理解
This is almost an equality but we're making floors
这几乎是个等式  但我们做了向下取整
so it's greater than or equal to.
所以是大于等于符号
And then, for each group median, we know that there are
对于每个组内中间值来说  我们知道
three elements there that are less than or equal to that group median.
有三个元素小于或等于这个组内中间值
So, by transitivity, they're also less than or equal to x.
因此根据传递关系它们也小于等于元素x
We get this number times three.
所以这个数还要再乘以3
This is actually just floor of n over 10.
这实际上就是n/10的向下取整
I was being unnecessarily complicated there,
前面我故意把这个式子写得比较复杂
but that is where it came from.
只是为了说明这个式子是怎么来的
What we know is that this thing is now at least 3 times n over 10,
现在我们知道这里至少是3*n/10
which is roughly 3/10 of elements are in one side.
也就是大概有3/10的元素在不等式的一边
In fact, at least 3/10 of the elements are in each side.
实际上不等式两边至少各有3/10的元素
Therefore, each side has at most 7/10 elements roughly.
因此不等号的两边最多有7/10的元素
So the number here will be 7/10.
所以这里的数字应该是7/10
And, if I'm lucky, 7/10 plus 1/5 is strictly less than one.
如果幸运的话  7/10+1/5肯定比1小
I believe it is, but I have trouble working with tenths.
我相信它成立  但是处理10进制还有些问题
I can only handle powers of two.
我只能处理2进制的情况
What we're going to use is a minor simplification,
所以我们还要再作一些简化
which just barely still works, is a little bit easier to think about.
这个简化过程比想象的要容易一些
It's mainly to get rid of this floor because the floor is annoying.
主要是把这个烦人的取整符号去掉
And we don't really have a sloppiness lemma that applies here.
实际上这里没有什么引理可用
It turns out if n is sufficiently large,
如果n足够大  那么
3 times floor of n over 10 is greater than or equal to n/4.
n/10的取整再乘以3一定比n/4大
Quarters I can handle.
n/4比较容易处理
The claim is that each group has size at least 1/4,
这表明每一个组至少是n/4个元素
therefore each group has size at most 3/4
因此每一个组最多是3n/4个元素
because there's a quarter on the side. This will be 3/4.
因为另一边是n/4元素  这里就是3/4
And I can definitely tell that 1/5 is less than 1/4.
显然1/5小于1/4
This is going to add up to something strictly less than one
加起来的话显然是小于1的
and then it will work.
这样就可以算了
How is my time? Good.
运行时间怎么样呢  好的
At this point, the rest of the analysis is easy.
分析到这里  剩下的部分就很简单了
How the heck you would come up with this algorithm,
这个算法到底怎么样
you realize that this is clearly a really good choice
你会意识到这是一种非常好的
for finding a partition element, just barely good enough
用来选择划分基准的方法  恰好能够
that both recursions add up to linear time.
使两部分递归加起来是线性时间
Well, that's why it took so many famous people.
这也是为什么这么多著名人物参与其中
Especially in quizzes, but I think in general this class,
在这门课上尤其是测试中  你们一般
you won't have to come up with an algorithm this clever
不会碰到这么妙的一个算法
because you can just use this algorithm to find the median.
因为你只能用这个算法来找中间值
And the median is a really good partition element.
中间值确实是非常好的划分基准
Now that you know this algorithm, now that we're beyond 1973,
现在你知道了这个算法而我们不是在1973年
you don't need to know how to do this.
你不需要知道具体是怎么回事
I mean you should know how this algorithm works,
我是说你应该知道这个算法是怎么算的
but you don't need to do this in another algorithm
但你不需要在另一个算法中写这个过程
because you can just say run this algorithm,
你只需要调用这个算法
you will get the median in linear time,
就能在线性时间内得到中间值
and then you can partition to the left and the right.
然后就能把一组数划分成左边和右边
And then the left and the right will have exactly equal size.
而左边和右边的元素个数恰好相等
Great.
太棒了
This is a really powerful subroutine.
这是一个非常有用的子程序
You could use this all over the place, and you will on Friday.
这个算法很常用  周五的练习就会用到
Have I analyzed the running time pretty much?
我分析过运行时间了吗
The first step is linear. The second step is T of n over 5.
第一步是线性时间  第二步是T(n/5)
The third step, I didn't write it, is linear.
第三步我还没写  是线性时间
And then the last step is just a recursive call.
最后一步是递归调用
And now we know that this is 3/4.
现在我们已经知道这是3/4
I get this recurrence. T of n is, I'll say at most,
可以得到这个式子  T(n)的上限是
T of n over 5 plus T of 3/4n.
T(n/5)+T(3n/4)
You could have also used 7/10.
你也可以用7/10代替3/4
It would give the same answer, but you would also need a floor
答案是一样的  但是多一个取整
so we won't do that. I claim that this is linear.
所以我们不那么做  我认为这是线性的
How should I prove it? Substitution.
怎么来证明呢  代换法
Claim that T of n is at most again c times n,
假设T(n)的上限是c*n
that will be enough.
那就足够了
Proof is by substitution.
用代换法证明
Again, we assume this is true for smaller n.
我们还是假设较小的数都满足这个式子
And want to prove it for n.
要证明对于当前n  这个式子也成立
We have T of n is at most this thing.
我们有T(n)的上限是这个式子
T of n over 5.
T(n/5)
And by induction, because n of 5 is smaller than n,
归纳法可以证明  因为n/5小于n
we know that this is at most c.
我们可以得到这里是
Let me write it as c over 5 times n.
写成c/5*n
Sure, why not.
好的
Then we have here 3/4cn.
然后这里是3/4*cn
And then we have a linear term.
接下来是一个线性项
Now, unfortunately,
现在  不幸的是
I have to deal with things that are not powers of two.
我不得不处理非二进制情况
I will cheat and look at my notes.
我要作弊地看一下我的笔记了
This is also known as 19/20 times c times n plus theta n.
这个式子就是19/20*cn+Θ(n)
And the point is just that this is strictly less than one.
显然这里是严格小于1的
Because it's strictly less than one, I can write this as one
因为这里严格小于1  我可以写成是
times c of n minus some constant, here it happens to be 1/20,
1*cn再减去某个常数  这里就是1/20
as long as I have something left over here,
只要结果和上面相同就可以了
1/20 times c times n.
1/20*cn
Then I have this annoying theta n term which I want to get rid of
然后是这个烦人的Θ(n)
because I want this to be nonnegative.
我想把它去掉因为我想让这里是负的
But it is nonnegative, as long as I set c to be really, really large,
但是只要c非常大  这里就是非负的
at least 20 times whatever constant is here.
取这里常数的20倍就可以了
So this is at most c times n for c sufficiently large.
所以只要c足够大  上限就是cn
And, oh, by the way, if n is less than or equal to 50,
顺便说一句  如果n小于等于50
which we used up here, then T of n is a constant,
我们在上面用到过  那么T(n)是一个常数
it doesn't really matter what you do,
不管怎么样
and T of n is at most c times n for c sufficiently large.
只要c足够大  T(n)的上限就是cn
That proves this claim.
这就证明了之前的假设
Of course, the constant here is pretty damn big.
当然  这里的常数相当大
It depends exactly what the constants and the running times are,
它依赖于这些常数和运行时间
which depends on your machine,
而它们都由你的机器性能来决定
but practically this algorithm is not so hot
但是实际上这个算法没有那么热门
because the constants are pretty big.
因为这些常数都相当大
Even though this element is guaranteed to
即使我们通过一些算法保证
be somewhere vaguely in the middle,
划分基准是中间值
and even though these recursions add up to strictly
即使这些递归加起来小于1
less than n and it's geometric,
并且还是几何级数的
it's geometric because the problem is reducing
说它是几何级数的是因为
by at least a factor of 19/20 each time.
问题的规模每次至少降低了19/20
So it actually takes a while for the problem to get really small.
实际上问题规模不会很快变得足够小
Practically you probably don't want to use this algorithm
除非你不会抛硬币  否则实际应用中
unless you cannot somehow flip coins.
你很可能不会想用这个算法
The randomized algorithm works really, really fast.
随机算法非常非常快
Theoretically this is your dream,
而理论上这确实是我们的梦想
the best you could hope for because it's linear time
它是线性时间  是能期望的最优算法
and you need linear time as guaranteed linear time.
你需要线性时间  有保证的线性
I will mention, before we end,
在下课之前  我还要提到
an exercise.
一个课后练习
Why did we use groups of five?
为什么我们要用五个元素为一组
Why not groups of three?
为什么不是三个元素为一组
As you might guess, the answer is because
你们也许已经猜到了
it doesn't work with groups of three.
因为三个元素为一组的话结果不成立
But it's quite constructive to find out why.
找出其中的原因是非常有用的
If you work through this math
如果你能算出用三个元素为一组
with groups of three instead of groups of five,
代替五个元素为一组的情况下问题的解
you will find that you don't quite
你会发现你本应该理解却没有理解的
get the problem reduction that you need.
问题的本质
Five is the smallest number for which this works.
5是这个算法能成功的最小数字
It would work with seven, but theoretically not any better
7个元素为一组算法也能成立
than a constant factor.
但是理论上来说性能不会提高很多
Any questions?
有问题吗
All right. Then recitation Friday.
好的  然后是星期五的习题课
Homework lab Sunday. Problem set due Monday.
实验室星期日开放  习题集下周一交
Quiz one in two weeks.
两周后测试